This is Wyatt, and on today's episode, I was joined by Isha Bharshani, head of ecosystem
at Sello Foundation. We talked at length about digital money usage in sub-Saharan Africa
and global stablecoin adoption patterns. I hope you enjoy our conversation.
Matt Walsh and Nick Carter are partners at Castle Island Ventures. All of these expressed
by them or the guests on this podcast are solely their opinions and do not reflect the
opinions of Castle Island Ventures. Guests and hosts may maintain positions in the assets
discussed in this podcast. You should not treat any opinion expressed by anyone on
this podcast as a specific inducement to make a particular investment or follow a particular
strategy, but only as an expression of their personal opinion. This podcast is for informational
purposes only.
Brought down by Bad Mortgage Investments, Lehman, which has 25,000 employees, will
be liquidated.
The federal government loans American International Group, AIG, $85 billion.
This is a different kind of market, and the Fed is asleep.
The federal government is stepping it to stabilize Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the two mortgage
giants that have been threatened by the housing crisis.
Bank of England has pumped 75 billion pounds more to Britain's ailing economy with a new
round of quantitative easing.
You print a couple trillion dollars and all of a sudden people start to worry. So out
of this worry, we have something called a Bitcoin. Bitcoin.
Esha, thanks for joining us on the podcast. Excited to talk to you today.
Thank you for having me. I'm really excited about our conversation today. I'm excited
to deep into a couple of really fun things that we've chatted about earlier.
Me as well. If you don't mind, please give a bit of a personal background and talk about
what you're doing these days.
Happy to. My name is Esha Varshley.
I head ecosystem at Salo Foundation.
Salo for people that are not aware is an EBM layer two blockchain.
And I've been head of ecosystem here for two years when I was hired to be head of DeFi.
Prior to this, I have a really interesting background, very not crypto native.
So did traditional finance before this?
I'm an accountant by profession.
Did M&A at a KPMG for a few years?
Did an MBA?
Did what everybody does typically after the MBA?
Went into traditional finance and private equity.
But the interesting thing about all of this is that I'm actually born and raised in Kenya.
After MBA, I went back home for a couple of holidays to see my parents.
And there was this massive fintech revolution happening on the continent,
specifically in that region of the world.
I had friends that had never been to Kenya, moving to Kenya to do all of these really cool,
interesting fintech jobs.
And I was like, oh, shit, I think I'm missing out.
And I never done tech before.
So I just rolled the dice, took a sabbatical for three months,
and I joined a regional bank that was setting up the digital banking unit.
And that was my first foray into tech.
We set up the digital bank, and the product is still a market leader in that region.
And then did a bunch of fintech consulting work.
You name it, from lending to wealth advisory to payments.
And that helped me understand what building a product and building a team in the tech space looks like.
Post which I had my own startup, obviously, as you do when you work in tech.
You have to do something of your own.
So I had a wealth tech, robot, advisory startup that was successfully bought out in a few years.
This was, think of it like the Acorn.
There was a few that are familiar.
It was very similar to the Acorn, focused in the Indian market.
And that did really well, so it did that.
And then once I got bought out, it was also COVID, had just moved to America.
It wasn't allowed to work because of the regulations around re-immigration here.
And so have this period of, what am I doing?
What is the next iteration of technology?
And then also, what is the next iteration of finance?
Because I went from traditional finance to fintech, and then obviously DeFi was the next obvious move.
And so I joined Selo as head of DeFi, like I mentioned.
And then at that point, we just announced something called DeFi for the people.
It was $100 million allocation to liquidity and grants and just encouraging the DeFi ecosystem in Selo.
And then as luck would have it, FDX happened straight after I joined.
And so that $100 million evaporated very, very quickly.
But I think in my mind, excellent timing, because I learned how to build in the bear.
I've been in the ecosystem during the bear.
Oh, we're only going to do DeFi to, oh, what is actual utility?
What is product market fit for Web 3?
And that's been a really interesting journey, especially at Selo,
because Selo, we're built for the real world.
We're constantly thinking about not only the crypto-native community, per se,
but we're thinking about how do we onboard users in emerging markets?
So when our typical user, somebody sitting in Kenya, in Nigeria,
and also given my background, it's really interesting to me,
because then we're thinking about, oh, what do these people need?
How do we bring them on chain and bring them on chain in a way that we abstract the technology aware?
How do we make it easier for them to interact on chain without them knowing they're dragging on chain?
And what is product market fit for this user base?
And so we'll talk a little bit more around how the ecosystem is built around a couple of things that I'm really passionate about.
But yeah, that's a little bit of my background and how I ended up at Selo.
You have a very holistic financial markets background, which is helpful for this subject.
What did you see in Kenya when you mentioned that financial revolution you talked about?
And when was this also?
So Kenya is a really interesting market.
We're talking about 2016-2017.
M-PASA is just starting up and it's just proliferating the market.
And so you're thinking about, in Nairobi, even today, I just carry my phone.
And I know it's happening more and more in the US where you use Apple Pay everywhere,
but in Nairobi, I've been living this for years.
You just take your phone and you have M-PASA on your phone and then that's it.
You don't carry a wallet and you can make every single payment through M-PASA.
And in that region on the M-PASA app, you have RoboAdvisor on the M-PASA app.
You have insurance on the M-PASA app.
Your whole world, it's like a super app.
It's become this super app system, but it just started with payments.
And so all your payments happened through M-PASA.
Can you talk about what M-PASA is for the audience?
M-PASA is mobile money.
It's run by Safari Calm.
It was essentially started as mobile money.
What they saw in Nairobi and in Kenya in a couple of different countries was getting
access to fiat was difficult.
So people started trading airtime, literally airtime, minutes on their phone.
Mostly people in the US and the developed world have plans and you don't think about
minutes on your phone or data minutes, but people started trading data minutes and they
were like, oh, wow, this is interesting.
We can make this into a currency.
It's the literal utility token.
Literally the utility token.
So they made it into a currency and they got nominated in a dollar into the Kenya Shilling.
It's literally mobile money.
So I can send you mobile money as actual currency.
It started with airtime.
It went into digitization of their currency.
So that's M-PASA.
And it started with just the payment system.
And then I think the beauty of this system was why it really shot up was you have this
mobile money on your phone.
But if you want cash for it, there's little vendors, little stalls everywhere that you
can go.
And it's similar to the off-ramping problem that we have currently in Web 3.
You can go to these kiosks they're called there.
And every little shop is a kiosk and you can go to the kiosk and say, hey, I have this
much M-PASA.
Can you give me cash?
There's obviously a spread for it.
And so most people don't want to off-ramp into actual cash, but you can do it if you
want.
And then even to on-ramp, you can go give them cash and then they can give you M-PASA.
And how much do you need cash given that M-PASA is in the system?
Today, zero.
Every single person takes cash.
When you think about micro payments in Kenya, at least the way I think about micro payments
in Kenya, I'm not talking about the coffees and the food and stuff like that.
I'm thinking about the guy that is taking money for parking.
And so it's not ticketed like this.
There's an actual person that's taking money for parking.
It's 10 or 20 shillings.
It's a very minimal amount.
120 shillings is $1.
So I'm talking about 10 or 20 shillings.
It's nothing.
It's fractions of the dollar.
And then even that person will take M-PASA.
So every single person you interact with will take M-PASA.
The guy who's selling you tea and tea there is in a little stall on the road selling it
on a little stool while sitting on another little stool.
Even he'll take M-PASA.
So I don't remember the last time I saw the shilling as a note, but that's just me.
And so ubiquitous in that region.
With that, because you digitize this, you digitize money.
With that came so many interesting use cases.
With that, the fact that you could scan your phone records, scan your SMS.
And every time you do an M-PASA transaction, you get an SMS saying, oh, 100 shilling deposited
or 200 shilling taken out of your account.
I could then, as a fintech, just ask you for the digital records of your messages.
You can't understand your entire financial history.
I'm not asking a bank for your financial statement.
I'm literally asking you for messages.
And so it opens up so many different use cases.
For instance, lending became really popular.
Here to peer lending?
Fintech lending.
For retail user, money in that region is really, really expensive.
I remember there was a period of time where I've seen, with my own self, 20% per month
is the rate of interest that you're paying and it accumulates.
You can imagine what that number becomes.
On an annualized basis, it's a ridiculous number.
You're paying 20% interest per month, but this allowed other players to go in and say,
oh, actually, we can lend money to you.
And the rates at which they were lending money wasn't competitive to what you get money at
from a bank in the US, but to the public in general on the ground over there, they were like,
oh, wow, this is so much cheaper.
And that's why fintech lending became so big there, because you could do M-PASA transactions.
Even e-commerce became a thing there because you've digitized money.
And the minute you digitize money, and we are all talking about this in the word crypto ecosystem,
but the minute you digitize money, so much more is possible.
And I'm talking like 2015, 10 years from today.
So it was a really interesting period to see that transition.
Another thing to maybe mention for your audience, and I'm sure they're not aware of this.
In the US, you can go into any bank and say, I want a retail banking account.
Most can kind of go in and say, hey, I want a retail banking account.
In some parts of the world, especially in sub-Saharan Africa,
retail banking is not a profitable business.
So even to get a bank account is really, really difficult.
So what are you left with?
And you're hoarding cash in your house, and crime levels are so high.
That's why M-PASA was so revolutionary, because you're like, oh, now I get access to banking
without actually having to go to a bank.
And it's funny when I was working at the bank, I was like, oh, wow,
we're going to set up a retail banking unit.
So now we're providing access to retail banking to a large part of the population.
And where we saw your salary would sweep into your account,
and there was an instant sweep out, literally instant,
where they'd sweep the entire monthly salary out into the M-PASA wallet.
So even when you get a bank account, because it had been so many years without banking,
they were like, OK, we prefer the M-PASA system.
So that's an interesting part of the world.
So I'm going to play this skeptic for a second, which is if M-PASA works,
why does currency need to be on chain?
Because M-PASA is not on chain.
M-PASA works, yes, but it works only in Kenya.
And people have tried to replicate the M-PASA use case across even African countries,
and it hasn't picked up for many different reasons.
M-PASA works because you have this massive Kiosk system that are on and off-run providers.
That system isn't there anywhere else in the world.
It's like Binance P2P.
Exactly like Binance.
Why is Binance so prolific in one specific region and not the others?
It's because of the P2P.
You have to know that you have access to your money and that they've given point of time,
and that's why M-PASA works.
Why are we digitizing?
So even with M-PASA, and we're seeing a lot of stablecoin usage in Kenyan,
we can talk about that a little bit more,
but we're seeing a lot of stablecoin usage in Kenya
is because the M-PASA is pegged to the shilling,
and the shilling as a currency against the dollar is not necessarily the strongest currency.
And that's why you need to digitize,
and getting access to dollars is more important in a lot of the world
than most of us understand.
So given that M-PASA works because of those vendors who will offer redemption,
do you think that is the unlock to mobile money systems,
whether on chain or otherwise, in other markets?
Or do you think there will be institutionalized on ramping off ramping?
Which will happen first?
That's a really good question. Depends on which markets.
You think it'll be different in each one?
I think it'll depend on every market.
Also, I think we were talking about 2015.
Technologies move so much.
I want to say 70% of my personal financial transactions happen online now,
as opposed to actually physical interactions.
So if you don't have off ramping in the physical world, not so critical now.
But again, it depends on which country and which region.
I'm sure some of the emerging markets having vendors and off-run providers on the ground,
little kiosks everywhere, will be critical for mass adoption.
But that's just my take. Who knows?
Yeah, it's interesting because it's always hard to imagine here in the US.
And I guess the reason for that is because each leg of our transaction is handled.
We have Venmo for peer-to-peer, and we have payment at a storefront.
But getting cash is still arguably a bit more of a pain than it should be in my life, for example.
I don't know if you've the same experience.
I don't remember the last time you used cash to me, honestly.
But again, I mean, you're removing cash from your financial transactions completely in the US
and in some of the more developed world.
But cash is king in a lot of countries even now.
And so in those countries where cash is king
and where you're actually doing a lot of daily transactions in cash,
you still need upfront providers that will go from any web-free currency
or even stablecoin to cash, so that at least having that as an option is important to on-board users.
And then eventually, when all your transactions and all your financial transactions go online or on-chain,
then it won't matter.
I've also learned that consumer behavior changes very quickly
if it's convenient and inexpensive.
If it reduces cost, time, effort, consumer behavior is easier to change than you would think.
Definitely, especially if there's not a great alternative.
So given that experience set, did Celo find you or did you find Celo or how did that come about?
I tell people this job was made for me.
So I was exploring Web3 and I did this fellowship program that GetCoin used to run called Kernel.
And one of the co-founders of Celo came to give an intro to Celo.
Just what he thought about Web3, he wasn't even talking about Celo.
He was talking about Web3 and the Mycelium network and things like that.
If you've ever heard steps, he's one of the co-founders of Celo.
If you've ever heard any of his talks, you will learn Mycelium and how everything is interconnected
and how financial systems are all interconnected and how we need to generate this whole new world
where we think differently from the existing structures.
And so he came on and I was like, well, that's a really good way to think about financial systems
and how we can reimagine financial systems.
And the Celo team was also doing this Kernel cohort.
And so I reached out to them once he came on and I was like, oh, I'd love to learn more.
And they were like, oh, cool.
That week fatted and they were like, oh, you have a bunch of developing country experience.
And we're looking for someone, would you consider interviewing?
And the rest, as I say, is history.
It's a great fit.
I know the regions that we target really well and work in those regions.
So it's like a really great fit.
My Mycelium exposure is the extent of a Netflix documentary called Fantastic Fun Guy,
but I'll have to get up to speed on the financial network side of it.
He describes it similar to how financial networks could be like the fungi network,
how it's all interconnected.
Yeah, I buy that.
It's an interesting conversation.
So what was Celo's mission when you joined and how has it evolved or stayed the same?
So we're very mission focused chain and our mission is prosperity for all.
And I don't think we've changed the mission.
So when you think about prosperity for all, everybody has a different take on this.
And you could have prosperity for all.
The way I kind of understand it is prosperity for all translates into financial inclusion,
just because I'm a finance background.
To me, I take it in from a financial perspective.
But prosperity for all from a different perspective is also very refined.
And so the Celo mission is essentially build and design for real world adoption of Web 3
that unlocks this mission of prosperity for all.
And when you think about real world adoption, because the chain,
we thought about emerging markets as a really big part of the world.
The chain is built in a way that is focused on inclusivity.
So we're very mobile first.
So all applications of Celo are mobile focused.
We have things such as fee abstraction.
So gas in the ecosystem can be paid in stable coins.
Because we understand my first crypto transaction didn't go through.
And I was sweating because I was like, oh, why is this not going through?
And then I realized, oh, I need another token for gas.
But if you are in this ecosystem or when you're onboarding to this ecosystem,
let's suppose you have only one wallet and the stable coin on that wallet,
you should be able to do the transaction with just the stable coin.
And that's the thought behind Celo.
OK, you can have one wallet with just a USDT or a USDC.
And then the transaction will go through because you can pay for gas.
So fee extraction is a really big thing.
There's ultra green money, which is inbuilt into the chain,
which is essentially like portion allocation of the gas fee goes towards carbon offsetting.
Like I mentioned, phone number mapping is really important
because we think most of the world interacts with technology
through their mobile phone as opposed to like a browser or a laptop.
The chain is built for, like I said, everyday use, everyday user.
But also the technology is really frontier.
We were the first POS chain.
And where are this really cool intersection of frontier tech and real world use case?
And I think that's where Celo will always remain.
I'm curious how you guys look at the balance,
given you're in the stable coin space at a global level,
between trying to provide better native systems for people globally
versus someone say there's value to offering dollars to people globally
as an alternative to their local financial systems.
So how do you strike the balance
and which if one of the two is more mission aligned with what you guys are doing?
That's a really good question.
I don't think we are picking a side because I don't think there's a side to be picked.
You need dollars in the world and access to dollars is really important
for users in specific countries.
Nigeria, for instance, is a really good example for that
where your currency kind of fluctuates on a weekly basis.
It's a 20-30% fluctuation on a weekly basis.
All of us talk about Bitcoin to be the store of value,
but actually for some people in the world, dollars are the store of value.
So having the nominated stable coins is really important in the ecosystem.
And so like I mentioned, we have native USDC and USDT
and CUSD as dollar-denominate stable coins
that are all gas currencies in the ecosystem.
But it's interesting when you provide access to dollars,
then a lot of really interesting cool applications get built on top of it.
And then users then want to go,
okay, so if dollars are store of value,
well, we actually need to do everyday transactions.
And so you need their local currencies for everyday transactions.
So currently in the ecosystem, we have, I think, 22 plus native stable coins.
And then I think that's between 12 to 14 different currencies.
And so a user can store value in dollar,
but then can move that to their local currency
and then use it for everyday transactions.
And then the other thing that I think most of us don't think about is,
if you just have dollars in any ecosystem, then how does lending happen?
Because if you're in markets where your local currency devaluates on a regular basis,
then not only are you paying interest on that loan,
you're also paying currency fluctuation,
which becomes really expensive sometimes.
So definitely no local currencies for some of these interesting use cases like lending.
Have you historically faced any pushback from nations or local regulators
when you're potentially offering dollars to people globally?
Not yet.
We're also committed to working with jurisdictions in every region that we operate
and we prioritize for compliance and benefits of users.
But to be honest, we are not a stable coin issuer per se.
We're just an ecosystem where stable coins that are issued by other entities
live within our ecosystem.
Yeah, it makes sense.
We're also really committed to making sure that we do our due diligence
when anything launches in our ecosystem
to make sure that they are talking to regulators or in specific conversations with them.
Why do you think non-USD stablecoins haven't emerged at broader scale yet?
Depends on what you think is broader scale.
So firstly, there were not so many non-USD stablecoins a year ago.
I think a lot more issuers are issuing non-USD stablecoins.
Within the last six to 12 months, I've seen a lot more non-USD stablecoins.
I also think that what is the product market fit for non-USD stablecoins
is lending and the FX market.
And for some of this to be true, it becomes a world in which you have to make sure
that there's a lot of depth of liquidity for this to make sense at all.
And you have to explain to the world what the use cases for this are.
So when you think about FX, when I used to live in, for instance, Africa,
when I was working in Africa, if you needed to go from the shilling to the Canadian CD,
you had to go shilling dollar and then you would spread there and then dollars,
the Canadian CD.
But now there's on chain stablecoins where you can go directly.
Mentor protocol is in protocol in the ecosystem, which is doing a lot of FX.
They were on the podcast last week.
That's perfect. I love that team.
They're a really great team.
And I'm sure they talked about how you can go from one currency to the other
without going through the dollar and things like that.
I think a revolutionary.
I just don't think the world's caught on yet.
I think with some of this patience is important.
We're a little bit ahead of what people are thinking about long term.
And again, depth of liquidity is really important.
So for this to be relevant and true,
you would need institutional capital providers to come in and deepen liquidity.
And I don't think that's happened yet.
And I think they're coming slowly, slowly.
They're looking at all of this slowly.
Yeah, I agree. I think it'll be lucrative.
It's so great.
It's all on chain.
Post of transacting is nothing.
Yes, it's nothing.
And spreads are incredible.
And it's also 24 seven.
The FX markets on chain are 24 seven.
Imagine trading that can happen.
Do you guys have an interest in also pursuing non fiat,
nominated stable coins or stable coin,
flat coin like products that might be tied to real estate or equities
or other asset classes like that?
I think those are really interesting.
I remember the promise of RWAs early days
of all of this tokenization of their assets.
Again, for some of this,
I really believe truly that liquidity is a key driver.
Am I going to tokenize a random mining asset
and I'm expecting retail to buy it?
No, not really.
I think retail will buy a small slice in that whole five.
So with the institutional capital providers looking at Web 3,
more scrutiny here in Web 3,
more liquidity coming to Web 3,
I think could make all of these things interesting.
Like I said, on chain markets are 24 seven,
which is not the case in any other markets.
So I think it'll be good to have tokenized versions of these assets,
but who's buying these assets is really important to look at.
From what we're seeing, it feels like the remittance apps
will be an early catalyst
in that all of a sudden you'll have real inflections in volume
of different stablecoins.
And once you have that,
that starts to tease in the liquidity providers
because they're like, okay, it's going to be lucrative
if I can take the other side of this very hefty trade.
And then maybe they'll stick around
and start to stand up other markets.
Because the point you made,
you can literally stand up FX markets,
which will be high volume relative
to an amount of liquidity provided
and should be a high return.
Absolutely. Just speaking of remittance,
I want to say remittance as a use case in my mind
is the perfect product market fit for Web 3,
where we are right now,
and stablecoins for where we are right now.
To give you an example,
we talked about Africa Focus for Salo for so much,
and we haven't talked about one of our main products,
which is Opera Mini Pay.
It's a collaboration with Opera, which is a browser product.
We integrated a stablecoin wallet into the browser,
and we've onboarded 7 million plus users on that browser product.
It's a stablecoin only wallet.
So you could only have USDC, USDT and CUSD on that wallet.
7 million plus people have onboarded it to it.
And then recently, we went and made it into a standalone app.
So it's currently available to all of you on Android or iOS,
and you can download it.
And in my mind, that will be the biggest catalyst
for cross-border remittance.
I mean, to be honest, the other day,
I sent my mom just on Mother's Day.
I couldn't find flowers online,
and it was really late at night,
but I'd forgotten Mother's Day.
I'm not a great daughter.
Just sent her some money saying,
hey, can you please buy yourself flowers today?
It's super simple. It settled in one second.
It was great, and I'm talking about a really trivial use case,
but remittance just in and out of Africa
is double-digit million on an annual basis.
And so if you can capture even a slice of this market,
that's big money.
If you've done cross-border remittance
of the traditional funds, in and out of Africa,
it takes seven days sometimes through the banking network,
and the spreads are ridiculous.
And if you're doing this on stablecoins, no spreads.
It's cents on the dollar for gas, and then you're done.
So I'm really excited about the mini-paste and loan app.
I would imagine a lot of the remittance piece
gets captured in there.
I was going to touch on opera,
so you brought it up in timely fashion.
With your business background,
do you think adoption will be more so through an opera
or a finance or yellow card product
that, to some degree, are accounts
that are a little bit more free-form,
where they give you access
and it's a little bit of, do what you like with it,
or more of a transfer-wise Felix-type experience
where it's a purpose-built remittance product
that links with existing accounts?
So it's funny, you've mentioned opera,
finance, and yellow card as competitors,
but it's interesting that opera actually uses yellow card
and finance for on and off and in the back.
I meant to group, though.
I shouldn't say I don't think they're competitors.
I think they have parallels.
They're all bundled into one product
for some of your audience that may not be familiar.
In some of the markets that we're talking about,
when you show somebody a dollar,
when you show them a dollar fiat currency,
they don't know what that is.
For them, dollar is USDT.
Really, in Nigeria, there's some areas
where they think of dollar as USDT.
In these areas, do I think the transfer-wise
will come on top?
Maybe not.
Do I think products like opera will come on top?
Absolutely.
So it depends market to market,
but I also think that this market is so big,
there is space for everybody to play.
It's also just a world in which a lot of this money movement,
it's a bunch of trust.
So opera specifically, I think they're well-positioned
because they have trust with the users
from their browser product already.
It's not a brand new branding going into the market
and saying, hey, use us for cross-border remittance.
People trust them.
So I think we have a really good finding chance,
but I also think that there's space for everybody to play.
This is a big market.
I think if transfer-wise comes up tomorrow,
and I don't know if they're already doing it,
I'm sure they're looking at this already,
but if transfer-wise comes up tomorrow and says,
hey, we'll do cross-border remittance through stablecoins,
I think there's a world in which everybody plays
in this market.
Different markets, I think, will have different people,
different products being taken up.
In Kenya, Nigeria, and some of these markets,
are you seeing a lot of business USDT accounts?
Yeah.
It's not us.
There's just so much.
Already, Sub-Saharan Africa, I will club.
Sub-Saharan Africa does so much cross-border settlement
with Asia, and a lot.
I want to say 70% of that settlement happens in USDT.
If I don't have my facts right, and again,
it's not official numbers that I'm getting,
but just based what I know, 70% of that settlement
happens in USDT.
So it's funny you say this.
We had launched Minipay as a retail product,
and what we learned was some of these people
that were settling B2B settlements
used to come and park some of their USDT on Minipay
when it was just a product in the browser, in Africa only,
because the yield on USDT on Minipay was really high.
What was the yield?
It was a ridiculous amount, just to form board.
And we were, again, far of context.
The average balance on Minipay wallet in Africa
is between $10 plus minus.
So these balances aren't very high,
so when you give them a yield of hypothetically 25% per annum
or more, that yield is not too much for the retail user.
But when you look at it from a commercial perspective,
if you're getting 25% on a dollar-denominate stablecoin,
that's a lot.
Nobody's giving you 25% yield on the dollar,
and so we saw a bunch of people park their money.
Like the B2B settlers and cross-border payments guys,
some of their money into Minipay accounts,
and we were like, oh, we're going to have cap
upper limits to balances for this yield activity,
but it was great to see people found it very organically.
And are you seeing financial products come on chain
in those local economies?
Yeah, so I'll give you an example.
We have a protocol in the ecosystem called Heraka that does.
So again, I'm a really big proponent of meat users
where they're at and not give them, like, hey,
this is a solution we've come up with.
You're going to have to fit your behavior to this solution.
And so in these regions, for instance,
SACOs or savings and lending groups are very popular.
And they're called different things.
In India, they're called Kitties.
And in Kenya, they're called SACOs.
And these groups are very prevalent across emerging markets.
And so we have a protocol in the ecosystem called Heraka,
which does microloans, and they're now starting saving.
So essentially, it's just like a savings and lending group
where you save and lend within a specific user group.
So you, me, and three of our friends, former group,
and we save and lend within each other.
And that's how it's done.
It's behavioral.
That's happened across generations in these regions.
And so when you bring that behavior on chain,
it becomes really easy.
Then you can do settlement.
You can do accounting.
Everything is on chain.
So Heraka, I think, is a really good example of that.
We're seeing people do employee payments.
There's a protocol called Franklin
that is doing stablecoin payments for payroll.
One of my favorite examples that just came online
in the ecosystem is this protocol called Bando.
And you can buy gift cards to places
like Target, Chipotle, Starbucks in the US,
but very specific to even the regions that we service.
So in Kenya and South Africa, you can get a gift card
to Shoprite, which is the target of that region.
And they have similar things than South America.
So really interesting products are coming on chain.
Some of them financial, some of them non-financial.
I'm going to give a shout out of one specific product
that is non-financial that I'm very fond of in the ecosystem.
It's a music streaming app called a Bando.
So think of it like Spotify.
The reason it's on mini-pay right now
is because you can pay on a daily basis.
You can take a daily subscription.
And again, for you and me, this seems ridiculous.
Like why would I want a daily subscription
to a music streaming app?
But for some of the regions that we're talking about,
the monthly music streaming subscription is really expensive.
So there's some days you can afford it
and some days you can't afford it.
And so the fact that you can break it down
to such minute levels and do it on-chain
with a little bit of a stablecoin is really interesting.
And in Bando, if you guys are listening,
has excellent music.
It's Afrobeat.
I love it.
It's what's playing in the background
when I'm doing deep focused work.
But really great.
We're constantly thinking about on-chain financial.
But like when some of these use cases come online
where you're like, hey, there's some music streaming app
that I could pay with stablecoins, that's cool.
I want to ask you one more question as we close out here,
which was given all this framing you've offered,
I'm a major believer that where we'll see value
in this on-chain economy is in these real use cases,
real assets.
Do you think blockchain platforms' applications
need to have native tokens or tokens for themselves?
Do you think that we need to have these,
I would call them internet money tokens
that the industry has been known for for a long time?
Or do you think eventually that fades into the background?
Funny you call them internet money.
My mom calls that magic being money.
So I don't know whether we should have them or not.
I know that in my ecosystem, this seller token
is there for decentralized governance.
And I think that's really, really critical.
I think one of the things that we're trying to do
in some form or the other,
and whether you explicitly say it or not,
is rebuild how any organization works
or how financial systems work.
That's why we're all in web three.
We're trying to reimagine some of this.
I think decentralized governance is one of those areas.
But I'm really like, this is a really cool thing.
I believe in collective intelligence.
And so decentralized governance
is a really good example of collective intelligence.
So the seller token, honestly,
one of the primary reasons to have seller token
is decentralized governance,
where the ecosystem and everybody in the community
decides what is the future for the chain.
So for instance, to give you a really good example,
we went from a layer one blockchain to a layer two blockchain.
We successfully migrated to a layer two blockchain.
But every single decision for the infrastructure
was done in public, really centralized governance.
And so every stack put out massive forum proposals
on the seller forum to say,
hey, this is why you should pick us.
So we had proposals from OB stack, from Arbitrum,
from Polygon ZK, from Matter Labs and things like that.
And there was such an incredible healthy discussion
in the community around which stack we should pick.
So it wasn't centralized decision.
It wasn't seller foundation or CLAP taking the decisions.
It's the community came together.
And I think some of the things that came up
in some of those community decisions,
I was like, oh, wow, we weren't even thinking about this.
And so I think collective intelligence
is really, really interesting.
Also what it did was we've heard from different sources.
If you're picking a layer two stack,
seller forum is like Wikipedia.
People actually go into the best seller forum to look at,
oh, when they're doing a stacking decision,
they go into the seller forum and look at,
oh, these are the things that were discussed.
This is what the answers were.
So I think decentralized governance is a really good example
of why you need native tokens or magic bean money
to buy things we need as many as we have right now.
I think there will be a world of consolidation,
but I don't know when that world will be,
but it's interesting.
We were talking about collective intelligence.
I think one of the reasons we specifically
have been successful as an ecosystem
is because we have regional DAOs also.
So we have a DAO in Africa.
We have a LATAM DAO.
We have a Thailand DAO.
We have a Philippines DAO.
And because we think that every region should have a say
in how we represent in that region.
These DAO communities have been incredible
and also very active in our governance process.
And so as we're thinking about how do we do
a go-to-market strategy for that specific DAO,
it's been really helpful to have the communities in there
have a massive say in some of those decision-making.
I'm big-proponent again of decentralized governance.
I know it has some flaws.
We've all experienced some flaws at decentralized governance,
but I think overall, if you're able to manage it,
I think incredible concept.
I'm excited to see where it evolves in the next five years.
I guess if you're going to have a digital financial system
or monetary system, you should have some form
of democratic monetary decision-making.
100% we're 100% aligned on that.
Well, Yisha, thank you for coming on.
I hope you come back to chat with us again soon.
Thank you for having me.
This was a lovely conversation.
I'm excited to see where this podcast grows and scales.
Thank you.
I appreciate it.
Thanks for listening to another episode
of On the Brink with Castle Island.
To find out more about Castle Island,
visit castleisland.vc.
To listen to all of our podcast episodes,
please go to onthebrink-podcast.com
or just click on the tab in our website.
Thanks for listening.